<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>uneven-aged forest management | Clément Hardy</title>
    <link>https://klemet.github.io/tag/uneven-aged-forest-management/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://klemet.github.io/tag/uneven-aged-forest-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>uneven-aged forest management</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024 Clément Hardy</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://klemet.github.io/media/icon_hu93a42bfcf8f1c81b76f58cb79681382c_22880_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>uneven-aged forest management</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/tag/uneven-aged-forest-management/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 Simulating forest roads is necessary to determine the impacts of forest management on habitat amount and fragmentation (QCBS)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-qcbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-qcbs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Poster_2021_Clement_Hardy.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is perceived as offering attractive trade-offs between wood production, and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties persist about its impacts, due to the distribution of harvesting areas and the construction of forest roads over larger areas than the most traditional even-aged development. We have been exploring these impacts on the composition and fragmentation of a landscape for more than a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this, we used the spatially explicit LANDIS-II simulation model and a new extension that simulates the evolution of the forest road network. We simulated 30 development scenarios in a landscape of the Mauricie region by varying the use of uneven-aged management methods and the aggregation of cuts. Our results show that, in comparison with even-aged management management, uneven-aged management increases the density and operational costs of the forest road network, the amount of forest with old tree cohorts, and the per se fragmentation of these forests. In addition, in the boreal forest to the north of the landscape, forest fires tended to fragment old forests despite forest management, reducing the differences between management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged management must depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation related to natural disturbances, and the perceived effects of per se fragmentation in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of cuts can reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but is unlikely to fully compensate for them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (University of Alaska Fairbank)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-university-of-alaska-fairbank/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-university-of-alaska-fairbank/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction extend over larger areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management on the composition and fragmentation of a 800 000ha landscape over a 150 years-planning horizon. To that end, we used the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension that simulates the expansion of the forest road network. We compared 30 different management scenarios that varied the proportion of even- and uneven-aged management, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads on a forested landscape of Mauricie (Québec, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences in landscape fragmentation between even-aged and uneven-aged management were reduced in the northern region of the landscape, in the boreal forest, where forest fires tended to fragment old forests irrespectively of the type of management approach employed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged over even-aged management should depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation resulting from natural disturbances, and on the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to compensate them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 🏆 Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (IBFRA)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-ibfra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-ibfra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🏆 This presentation won the &amp;ldquo;Best presentation&amp;rdquo; award for this annual conference of the IBFRA&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction can impact the composition and fragmentation of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management at the landscape scale and on a planning horizon of 150 years by using the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension allowing for the dynamic simulation of the forest road network. We simulated a landscape containing boreal forest in the Mauricie Region of Québec with 30 different management scenarios where we varied the use of uneven-aged management methods, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that when compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests of the landscape, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences of fragmentation of the landscape between even-aged and uneven-aged management were lower in the northern region containing more boreal forest, as forest fires tended to fragment the old forests of the landscape in spite of any forest management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that selecting uneven-aged over even-aged management should be closely linked to how fragmentation and habitat are defined, to the patterns of fragmentation as a result of natural disturbances, and to the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help to reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to entirely compensate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 Simulating forest roads is necessary to determine the impacts of forest management on habitat amount and fragmentation (ESA)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-esa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-esa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Poster_ESA_V4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services related to biodiversity conservation, carbon storage, and social acceptability. While benefits of uneven-aged management have been reported at the stand-scale and for short time periods, uncertainties remain concerning its impacts for longer time periods and broader spatial scales. Of concern is the impact of forest roads. Indeed, uneven-aged forestry requires that silvicultural operations extend over larger forest areas than even-aged forestry in order to harvest the same volume of wood. Consequently, uneven-aged forestry may require a larger and more permanent forest road network to reach distant stands over shorter rotation periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management on the composition and fragmentation of a 800 000 ha landscape over a 150 years-planning horizon. We used the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension that simulates the expansion of the forest road network. We compared 30 different management scenarios that varied the proportion of even- and uneven-aged management, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads on a forested landscape of Mauricie (Québec, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests, but also the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences in landscape fragmentation between even-aged and uneven-aged management were reduced in the northern region of the landscape, in the boreal forest, where forest fires tended to fragment old forests irrespectively of the type of management approach employed. We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged over even-aged management should depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation resulting from natural disturbances, and on the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to compensate them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🛠 Workshop to learn to use the FRS module for LANDIS-II</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/workshop-to-learn-to-use-the-frs-module-for-landis-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/workshop-to-learn-to-use-the-frs-module-for-landis-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Forest Roads Simulation (FRS) module is an extension of the LANDIS-II Forest Landscape Model (FLM). It was created so as to help researchers in ecology to take into account the constructions of forest roads when studying the impacts of forest management on forest landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/frs-module-workshop/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://klemet.github.io/frs-module-workshop/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 🏆 Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (CEF)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-cef/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-cef/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🏆 This presentation won the &amp;ldquo;Best presentation&amp;rdquo; award for this annual symposium of the CEF&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction can impact the composition and fragmentation of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management at the landscape scale and on a planning horizon of 150 years by using the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension allowing for the dynamic simulation of the forest road network. We simulated a landscape containing boreal forest in the Mauricie Region of Québec with 30 different management scenarios where we varied the use of uneven-aged management methods, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that when compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests of the landscape, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences of fragmentation of the landscape between even-aged and uneven-aged management were lower in the northern region containing more boreal forest, as forest fires tended to fragment the old forests of the landscape in spite of any forest management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that selecting uneven-aged over even-aged management should be closely linked to how fragmentation and habitat are defined, to the patterns of fragmentation as a result of natural disturbances, and to the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help to reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to entirely compensate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 The influence of forest road networks on the long term impacts of uneven-aged management</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/the-influence-of-forest-road-networks-on-the-long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/the-influence-of-forest-road-networks-on-the-long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services such as biodiversity conservation, carbon storage, and social acceptability. While the benefits of uneven-aged management have been reported at the stand-scale and on short time periods, uncertainties remain concerning the impacts of uneven-aged management on longer time and wider spatial scales. Of concern are the impact of forest roads, as uneven-aged management necessitate more permanent roads and an increased road usage in order to accommodate shorter harvest rotations. These could in turn increase permanent forest lost, fauna road mortality, carbon emissions and operational costs for the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore this question, we compared the impact of uneven-aged management with that of even-aged management at large time and spatial scales. We created a road extension for the LANDIS-II landscape simulation model, whose goal is to simulate the construction of forest roads to reach harvesting areas in a dynamic and spatially explicit way. Road trajectories are computed by minimizing construction costs according to existing roads, elevation, topography, water bodies, and soil types. We developed 20 scenarios with different proportions of harvested areas managed with uneven-aged or even aged management methods, for a given harvest wood volume. The scenarios also differed in the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and in the presence of a pre-existing forest roads. We tested these scenarios over a planning horizon of 300 years on a landscape of 5 million hectares in Mauricie, Canada, and measured several characteristics of the road network for each scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results will further our understanding of the long-term impacts of management strategies in forested landscapes, and will also open new opportunities to explore the impact of forest roads around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 Roads to conservation</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/roads-to-conservation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/roads-to-conservation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The caribou (Rangifer tarandus) faces many different pressures throughout Québec, making it a vulnerable species. In particular, forest roads, numerous throughout the province, increase caribou mortality. Indeed, forest roads increase predation by the grey wolf (Canis lupus) that uses them to move quickly through the landscape to track its prey. Moreover, forest roads also increase habitat fragmentation; which in turn generates stress, habitat avoidance, and ultimately affect feeding patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ministère des Forêts, de la Faune et des Parcs du Québec (MFFP), in charge of forest management and fauna protection, is faced with the difficult task of designing forest roads necessary to maintain the viability of the forest industry while reducing their negative impact on the caribou. As part of an internship at the MFFP, I have developed an open-source GIS-based tool capable of exploring different strategies for building forest road networks. The goal of this tool is to prevent the disturbance of areas important to the caribou populations, and to detect existing roads that could be removed in order to improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool had to respect many criteria: it had to be quick and easy to use, while being flexible enough to explore different user-defined scenarios. Each scenario generates a forest road network that expands across the forest areas to be harvested. In this presentation, I will briefly describe the difficulties faced to solve the very complex problem of optimizing a road network. I will also explain how I simulated the wood flux through the network in order to determine its most important roads.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 A new LANDIS-II module to study the effects of roads on forest landscapes</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/a-new-landis-ii-module-to-study-the-effects-of-roads-on-forest-landscapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/a-new-landis-ii-module-to-study-the-effects-of-roads-on-forest-landscapes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./poster_final_colloque_cef_2019.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LANDIS-II is a spatially explicit model to simulate the evolution of a forest landscape represented by a raster. Each cell in it represents a piece of the surface of it, and the LANDIS-II user can choose from different extensions in order to represent processes that impact the plant succession of the landscape forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the existing extensions make it possible to model forest fires, biological epidemics, chablis, and the effect of logging on wood harvesting. However, the goal of the LANDIS-II Foundation, which is responsible for the development of the model, is more ambitious: interested researchers are explicitly invited to develop new extensions thanks to a structure that allows extensions to be easily grafted onto the &amp;ldquo;heart&amp;rdquo; of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in this context that our research project fits in, which aims to explore the effects of equitable and inequal forest management methods on large spatial and temporal scales. The more extensive uneven-aged forest management methods are currently presented by many researchers as an important alternative to the even-aged methods, but the impacts of their use have not yet been considered on a large scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To distinguish the effects of these methods at the landscape scale, however, we must take into account a process that has, to our knowledge, never been modeled in such a context: the construction of forest paths necessary for access to stands. To this end, we have started the development of a new extension for LANDIS-II. This extension will simulate the development and maintenance of a network of forest paths in a landscaped landscape, and the costs and effects associated with these paths. We will combine the use of this module with different forest management scenarios, in order to observe how the use of the Equian and Inequian methods influence the quantity and structure of paths in the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📊 How do I cut this forest landscape for you? - Influence of space tessellation methods on modeling in forest ecology</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/how-do-i-cut-this-forest-landscape-for-you-influence-of-space-tessellation-methods-on-modeling-in-forest-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/how-do-i-cut-this-forest-landscape-for-you-influence-of-space-tessellation-methods-on-modeling-in-forest-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, thanks to the increase in the computational capabilities of our computers, the fields of ecology and forestry have seen the appearance of new tools within them. Among these are spatially explicit models, in which processes and represented entities are placed in space. These models, now widely used and developed in number, then make it possible to simulate different scenarios to better understand or better predict the evolution of a studied system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to simplify the use of these models and the calculations they generate, the spatial dimension of the model is generally &amp;ldquo;discretized&amp;rdquo;. By this act, the space is then divided into more or less small cells depending on the resolution used. The geometric shape most used by modelers to cut out space is that of the square, which makes it possible to create regular grids, in addition to other advantages. This choice of geometry to discretize space can however be questioned, while it has been shown that it could have strong impacts on the results of a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then decided to focus on the impact of this choice on the functioning of spatially explicit models in forest ecology. For this, we will reproduce the operation of several existing models well known in the field, and which represent an important process for forest ecosystems (e.g. natural disturbances). We will then run these models on different grids (e.g. square, hexagonal, irregular, etc.) to observe the effects of these on the results obtained. Results obtained from preliminary work suggest that such effects may indeed be important, but not for all types of processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
