<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Clément Hardy</title>
    <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://klemet.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Clément Hardy</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://klemet.github.io/media/icon_hu93a42bfcf8f1c81b76f58cb79681382c_22880_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Veganism and climate change</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/veganism_and_climate_change/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/post/veganism_and_climate_change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So called &amp;ldquo;vegan&amp;rdquo; diets and lifestyle have been a subject of debate, controversy, but also interest those past few years. The number of people trying this lifestyle &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2020/oct/26/veganuary-movement-plant-based-food#:~:text=The%20UK%2Dbased%20campaign%2C%20which,2019%20and%20170%2C000%20in%202018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;have been soaring in the last decade&lt;/a&gt;; activists have been publishing more and more &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominionmovement.com/watch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;well-known documentaries revealing the dark side of animal agriculture&lt;/a&gt;; and many scientific studies have been advocating for the potential benefits of the lifestyle for the environment and climate change, as echoed by a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/srccl/chapter/chapter-5/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;special report of the IPCC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for many of us, veganism is a difficult and touchy subject. The whole concept can feel like an undeserved attack on traditions, jobs, or on other things that we hold dear. And yet, most of us agree with its ethical premises : we don&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of hurting or killing animals when it&amp;rsquo;s not needed for our survival, and especially not when it&amp;rsquo;s for pleasure, comfort or habits. The resulting tension between following our principles and trying to protect things we hold dear can lead to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20200203-the-hidden-biases-that-drive-anti-vegan-hatred&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;severe anti-vegan bias&lt;/a&gt; that can be quite hard to overcome. I know that it has been hard on me for quite some time, and that I&amp;rsquo;m not completely free of it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bias, associated with the incredible economic and ideological power of the animal agriculture industry, can make things hard to piece out when we look at the science behind vegan lifestyles. Some studies funded by the industry have been criticized by the scientific community; while the results of others have been exaggerated by activists to fit their narrative. &lt;a href=&#34;https://sydneyuniversitypress.com.au/products/128398&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Whole books are now dedicated to analyzing the process of deception&lt;/a&gt; steaming from there forces. Really, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big current talking point about veganism concerns its ability to help us reduce our impacts on the environment, and especially on climate change. If one should summarized why in two sentences, we could say that it&amp;rsquo;s all about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_efficiency&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ecological efficiency&lt;/a&gt; : at each level of a food chain, a great amount of energy coming from the level before is lost. Therefore, eating animals or they secretions imply that a great deal of the energy given to them as food - plants - will not be transformed as food for humans, but lost for the metabolism of the animal that is fed from. Meanwhile, eating plants avoids this loss - doubly so because plants are &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autotroph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;autotrophic beings&lt;/a&gt;. This is why, in a very paradoxical way, eating plants instead of animals means that we require much less plants to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I got interested in this subject, I came into the opportunity of updating an article concerning veganism on the famous website &lt;a href=&#34;https://skepticalscience.com/veganism.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skeptical Science&lt;/a&gt;, made by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.climatechangecommunication.org/portfolio-view/john-cook/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Cook&lt;/a&gt; and his colleagues. While not perfect by any mean, I always admired the attempt at scientific rigor and communication that the site strives for. And so, after rounds of writing and peer-review, my version is now online. I think that it does a pretty great job at giving a broad picture of the topic, and its subtleties. The short answer is that yes, veganism can be a great way to reduce our impacts on the environment, with a pretty clear consensus emerging from recent studies and reports; but that it won&amp;rsquo;t save the world by itself, and that other behavioral changes (like not using a car or not taking the plane) have a bigger impact on our &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_footprint&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;climate footprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://skepticalscience.com/veganism.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Wanna check out my article on Skeptical Science ? Click here !&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is just touching the &amp;ldquo;environmental&amp;rdquo; argument for veganism, and not even touching the other environmental aspects (such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/environmental-impacts-of-food&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;land-use, freshwater use, eutrophication, and biodiversity&lt;/a&gt;). Whatever the truth of the matter, I believe that our ethics always go first; that&amp;rsquo;s why none of us would start eating dogs, even if it was clearly proven that this would help fight climate change. Because of this, I recommend taking a closer look at what it really is to kill an animal; to imagine what we would feel if we were the ones slicing their throat, and facing their terrified gaze, all in order to eat a steak whose taste will be forgotten in a matter of minutes. And that if it is something that we couldn&amp;rsquo;t do ourselves out of compassion and kindness, maybe it is something that we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pay for either.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 types of software you should start using for your research</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/3_softwares_to_use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/post/3_softwares_to_use/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As human knowledge accumulates and our daily lives become ever more busy, it&amp;rsquo;s not wonder that we start feeling overwelmed as researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our human brain might be an amazing tool to discover and understand the world around us when compared to a cat&amp;rsquo;s or a dog&amp;rsquo;s equivalent, but it is still both biased and limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, there exist many different tools that can help us to compensate for these issues. And the wonderful news is that they are &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, that they do not contain advertising, and that they do not sell information about yourself or your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of 3 open-source software that changed my life as a PhD student and early researcher, by allowing me to &lt;strong&gt;organize my references, my notes and my files&lt;/strong&gt; like never before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;joplin&#34;&gt;Joplin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Joplin_logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joplin is a note-taking application with many features.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an open-source and completely free software that allows you to create notes in the &amp;ldquo;Markdown&amp;rdquo; writing language, and to organize them in &amp;ldquo;notebooks&amp;rdquo;, and associate them with tags. &lt;strong&gt;It is an excellent alternative to software such as Evernote or Microsoft One Note&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, Joplin allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather all your written or graphic information in one place&lt;/strong&gt;: your class notes, your thoughts, your projects, your recipes, your shopping lists, your to-do lists, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find all this information very quickly&lt;/strong&gt; (in a few seconds) thanks to the search tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use it on any computer&lt;/strong&gt; (Windows, Mac, Linux) and &lt;strong&gt;on any phone&lt;/strong&gt; (android, IOs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synchronize your data on the cloud you choose&lt;/strong&gt; : Nextcloud (see below), Google Drive, One Drive, etc. So you can have all your data written everywhere, all the time, on any media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a fully customizable interface&lt;/strong&gt; that allows you to focus totally on what you are writing, so that you don&amp;rsquo;t waste time and attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export your notes in many ways&lt;/strong&gt;, with a format (markdown) that can be read anywhere and at any time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically manage the images and files you insert in your notes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically edit your notes&lt;/strong&gt; (so you can go back at any time if you made a mistake).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And much more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joplin is an amazing software to try your hand at note-taking tools, and maybe even at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; method !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other wondful alternatives include &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zettlr.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zettlr&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;. However, I think that Joplin is the best place to start if you&amp;rsquo;re not used to such apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download Joplin, take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://joplinapp.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;zotero&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./zotero_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zotero is a bibliography management software.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having complete and rigorous bibliography information is necessary in academic documents (thesis, dissertation, article). It can also be very important for blog or website posts, videos, scripts, and many others. It can additionally be very useful for managing personal resources. The bibliography information of a document is called &amp;lsquo;meta-data&amp;rsquo;, i.e. data &lt;em&gt;about the document&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;outside the document&lt;/em&gt; (its title, its publication date, its author(s), etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zotero allows you to :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easily save all the metadata associated with a document&lt;/strong&gt; (title, authors, place of publication, date, URL, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Associate notes or tags&lt;/strong&gt; to each reference or document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sort these references by category&lt;/strong&gt;s, or by their characteristics to find them easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download associated PDF files&lt;/strong&gt; when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export bibliography files&lt;/strong&gt; that contain all the details of the references, so that they can be inserted into a document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insert and manage the bibliography of a document&lt;/strong&gt; in Microsoft Word, Libreoffice or Google Doc using its plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zotero have a wonderful community that devellops incredible plugins such as Better BibTex, Zotfile or MDnotes. All of these will allow you to connect your Zotero database to other software such as Joplin, Zettlr and Obsidian, or to export the annotations that you make in your &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download Zotero, you can go on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;nextcloud&#34;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Nextcloud_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nextcloud is a cloud software like Google Drive, allowing to host files, but also containing multiple very useful applications. However, unlike Google Drive, it is open-source and free&lt;/strong&gt;. You only need to host it on a server yourself, or choose an host (free, or subscription-based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have an online file storage space that is totally yours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have access to lots of different applications all open-source&lt;/strong&gt; that allow you to manage to-do lists, &lt;em&gt;kanban boards&lt;/em&gt;, calendars, contacts, notes, recipes, maps, track your phone&amp;rsquo;s location, collaborate on documents, and much more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud is an incredible way to boost your productivity by organizing simply across devices, and I cannot recommand it enough. It is also perfect to host your Joplin notes in the cloud, or your Zettlr or Obsidian files. You can even save the &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; files of your zotero database with it ! Best of all, most of Nextcloud&amp;rsquo;s apps can synchronize very easily with your phone. Tasks on your phone ? Check. Calendar ? Check. Kanban boards ? Check. Recipes ? Check. The list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find an host or download nextcloud and host it yourself, you should look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextcloud.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the project&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;remember-to-contribute-&#34;&gt;Remember to contribute !&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these incredible programs are free, but they all represent hours and hours of hard work, along with the work of creating documentation, beautiful websites, and easy-to-use installer for people like you or me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using open-source software can be describe as a particular way of life, as these are often much more respectful of your privacy than software made by companies such as Microsoft, Google, Facebook, or even Macintosh. But the price to pay is often on the shoulder of the devellopers : they are the ones investing the work needed, and will often have nothing for themselves if the venture fails, with no add revenues or revenues from selling your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, &lt;strong&gt;if you start using one of these programs, remember to take the time to make a donation or a contribution to the project that they represent&lt;/strong&gt;. If the software pleases you, the team behind it have certainly earned it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;want-to-know-more-&#34;&gt;Want to know more ?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Logo_atelier_organisation_EN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about these software, how to use them and their functionalities, you should take a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;free online workshop&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve created to help you discover them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just an afternoon before you, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn the most important thing about them; but you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn some great methods to use them properly, and even in tandem together !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
