<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Clément Hardy</title>
    <link>https://klemet.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://klemet.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Clément Hardy</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Clément Hardy</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://klemet.github.io/media/icon_hu93a42bfcf8f1c81b76f58cb79681382c_22880_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Clément Hardy</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis and predictions</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/hypothesis_and_predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/post/hypothesis_and_predictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s a prediction, not an hypothesis&amp;rdquo; read the comment of one of my co-author. He was right : what I did present as one of the hypotheses of my research paper was, in fact, a prediction. But then, I started to notice that a majority of the articles I read seemed to do the same mistake. A couple of days ago, I read the following in a recent article in ecology (which I&amp;rsquo;m paraphrasing) :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hypothesize that climate warming and the increase in CO2 concentration will increase forest productivity and carbon stocks in our modeled landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is indeed a prediction disguised as an hypothesis. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty hard to see, and pretty easy to miss; but apparently, the consequences for science can be more dire than I imagined at first, when the problem was revealed to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-epidemic-of-confusion&#34;&gt;The epidemic of confusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prevalence of this confusion is not a new phenomenon. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;In 2001, Guy R. McPherson wrote an article&lt;/a&gt; pointing to the fact that a certain amount of scientists did not know how to make the difference, which lead to this kind of error in research papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these discussions begin with a question I pose to PhD. students at their oral comprehensive examination: &amp;ldquo;What is a hypothesis?&amp;rdquo; When I first began asking this question more than 10 years ago, nearly all students invoked Popper&amp;rsquo;s falsificationist view (e.g. Popper 1981), then proceeded to confuse hypothesis with prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another personal anecdote reinforces the view that scientists (including those outside my academic institution) may confuse &amp;ldquo;hypothesis&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;prediction.&amp;rdquo; In a recent manuscript, my co-author and I substituted the inappropriate term &amp;ldquo;hypothesis&amp;rdquo; for the appropriate term &amp;ldquo;prediction&amp;rdquo; throughout the manuscript (a total of seven times). The paper was submitted to a major international journal in 1998 and was subjected to a high level of scrutiny by three reviewers (presumably scientists who are reasonably well known), the associate editor, and the editor-in-chief (the latter two individuals are internationally renowned scientists). None of the five individuals in the review process commented on the inappropriate use of &amp;ldquo;hypothesis,&amp;rdquo; and the manuscript was published in the journal in 1999 (corrections were noted by the co-authors on the page proofs, and incorporated in the published manuscript).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McPherson, 2001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not believe that this problem is due to the fact that PhD students and researchers are not smart enough to grasp the difference; nor that it comes from a real desire to disguise one into the other. It could be due to the fact that the difference is not taught enough - or not well enough - in the university, or even before that. In fact, McPherson&amp;rsquo;s article was published in &lt;em&gt;The American Biology Teacher&lt;/em&gt;, and was first and foremost directed at science educators. If our teachers don&amp;rsquo;t know the difference well enough, it&amp;rsquo;s understandable that most student won&amp;rsquo;t know it past their diplomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again, I do not believe that any blame is to be given to science educators : it&amp;rsquo;s simply that the difference between hypothesis and predictions can be very subtle, and that it is easy to be influenced by the work or words of others that confuse the two. Hence, we end up in a kind of &lt;a href=&#34;http://datanuggets.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/Strode_NABT-2011-Hypothesis-Presentation.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;epidemic of confusion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-real-difference-between-hypotheses-and-predictions&#34;&gt;The real difference between hypotheses and predictions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;predictions&#34;&gt;Predictions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we try to explain the difference between an hypothesis and a prediction, that&amp;rsquo;s where we start to see where the problem lies : it&amp;rsquo;s not always that easy to distinguish the two. From my understanding, there is no single method to be assured of what we&amp;rsquo;re doing, but only a set of clues. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to summarize them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-magic-8-ball-from-frankieleonhttpswwwflickrcomphotosarmydre20086521326205-on-flick&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./magic_8_ball.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A magic 8 ball from [frankieleon](https://www.flickr.com/photos/armydre2008/6521326205) on Flick.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A magic 8 ball from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/armydre2008/6521326205&#34;&gt;frankieleon&lt;/a&gt; on Flick.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we can say that a prediction is an affirmative statement about what will happen in certain conditions : they are all about patterns that can be observed. Most of all, as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McPherson (2001)&lt;/a&gt; points out, a &lt;strong&gt;prediction&lt;/strong&gt; does not need the scientific method to be validated or invalidated (in contrast to an hypothesis). In fact, we test predictions in our daily life without using any science at all. Even fortune tellers do it. Here are a couple of examples :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The salt is in this section of the supermarket&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pastas are ready&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will rain tomorrow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these are predictions, and only require observation - not experimentation - to be validated or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where it gets trickier is when we see predictions that concern things that are not in our daily lives, but that seems to touch the realm of &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo;. When they do, we might think that we are looking at an hypothesis. See the following statements :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no living organisms on Mars&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Climate change will reduce the resilience of forests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An increase in protein X will lead to disease Y&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know about you; but I&amp;rsquo;m personally are much more inclined to identify those as hypotheses. But nothing has really changed were compared to the three statement regarding &amp;ldquo;everyday life&amp;rdquo; : we&amp;rsquo;re still making affirmations about something that will happen in certain conditions, which is a prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there&amp;rsquo;s an important catch that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McPherson (2001)&lt;/a&gt; explains : that while testing predictions does not require the scientific method, it is in itself part of the scientific method, and part of what we call &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; overall. This is because sometimes, we have to just test a prediction to advance; wherever it is in order to validate or invalidate an hypothesis (that&amp;rsquo;s what is required to do it, after all), or because we need more information to formulate an hypothesis, or because the answer is really needed in the current context. &lt;strong&gt;Predictions are not &amp;ldquo;bad science&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;; they are a tool used by science, and necessary to science. The problem lies in confusing them with hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hypotheses&#34;&gt;Hypotheses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good way to identify an hypothesis is to see if the statement it contains can be an answer to a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. This is because hypotheses should be propositions related to how a system function, which can then be tested by using an experiment. Of course, any hypothesis should be falsifiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at a simple example : we have a flashlight that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Why doesn&amp;rsquo;t the flashlight work ?&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is a good example of a research question.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But if we say &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Is the flashlight not working because the batteries are empty&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, we&amp;rsquo;re already making an implied hypothesis, since we&amp;rsquo;re giving an explanation for why the system (the flashlight) works as it does. One thing at a time !&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The flashlight doesn&amp;rsquo;t work because the batteries are empty&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is a hypothesis : it answers the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;, and can be falsified.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another hypothesis can be &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The flashlight doesn&amp;rsquo;t work because the light bulb is broken&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now that we have the hypothesis, we can propose an experiment to test it : we can change the batteries, and see if the flashlight will work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, we can make a prediction that will come true if the hypothesis is validated : &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The flashlight will light up when we change the batteries&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important thing, according to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McPherson (2001)&lt;/a&gt;, is to distinguish the hypothesis (a statement about how the system functions) with the &lt;em&gt;statistical&lt;/em&gt; hypothesis (which is really a prediction : a statement about the statistical pattern that we should observe &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the hypothesis is true).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-light-bulb-is-a-good-example-to-distinguish-the-prediction-and-hypothesis--saying-that-changing-it-will-make-the-light-work-is-a-prediction-saying-that-the-light-doesnt-work-because-the-light-bulb-needs-to-be-changed-is-a-hypothesis&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./lightbulb.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The light bulb is a good example to distinguish the prediction and hypothesis : saying that changing it will make the light work is a prediction. Saying that the light doesn&amp;#39;t work because the light bulb needs to be changed is a hypothesis.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The light bulb is a good example to distinguish the prediction and hypothesis : saying that changing it will make the light work is a prediction. Saying that the light doesn&amp;rsquo;t work because the light bulb needs to be changed is a hypothesis.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we come back to the first example that I gave of a prediction hiding as an hypothesis, the real hypothesis would be :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hypothesize that climate warming and CO2 concentration affects forest productivity and carbon stocks at the landscape scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to test this hypothesis is to make a modeling experiment : &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;if&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; we model a forest landscape with increasing climate warming and C02 concentration, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;then&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; we should see the productivity and carbon stocks increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the article is recent, and the idea that climate warming will increase forest productivity in some forests in some ways is already well known; it&amp;rsquo;s safe to say that this is not the hypothesis that the authors wanted to test. But because it is not formulated in the right way, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to know what kind of information we will get in the end. And that&amp;rsquo;s one of the risks associated with making this confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a summary, a good way to identify an hypothesis (from my own point of view) is to see if it fits in the following sentence :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;experiment&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;then&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;prediction&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;because&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;hypothesis&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-it-so-important-to-distinguish-the-two-&#34;&gt;Why is it so important to distinguish the two ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confusing hypotheses and predictions can be more problematic that we might think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first problem is that by doing so, we can &lt;strong&gt;give wrong impression about what the scientific method is to the public&lt;/strong&gt;, and especially to students and young people. If we present the act of making a prediction and testing it with an observation as science, then many things that we do in our daily lives is &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt;. Checking if the salt is in this sections of the supermarket is a good example : it&amp;rsquo;s as much science as saying &amp;ldquo;putting batteries into the flashlight will make it work&amp;rdquo;. It is &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of the scientific method, but it&amp;rsquo;s not enough. Making a prediction and validating it doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer a lot of information in itself; especially if we didn&amp;rsquo;t take the time to design them so as to answer the real hypothesis as best we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second problem is that when researchers do this confusion, they show that they do not completely grasp the scientific method. &lt;strong&gt;This might be a contributing factor to the many problems that science is facing today&lt;/strong&gt; : the bias of publication towards studies that &amp;ldquo;validate hypotheses&amp;rdquo; or predictions; the fact that confounding factors are not taken into account while designing the experiment or observation made in the study; the lack of replicability ; the difficulty of synthesizing many studies that concern a particular topic; the misinterpretation of statistical analysis; and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third problem is that it prevents us from &lt;strong&gt;recognizing research that is done without testing an hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;. As &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/4451093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;McPherson (2001)&lt;/a&gt; states, most research in biology describes patterns rather than testing the mechanisms underlying of the patterns : and that&amp;rsquo;s OK. Not all research articles need to have an hypothesis, as a big part of formulating hypotheses and putting the scientific method to work is investigating patterns. For example, one would not test the hypothesis &amp;ldquo;tobacco causes lung cancer&amp;rdquo; without a previous investigation of the prevalence of lung cancers in tobacco smokers. Such an investigation would be part of &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; as a whole, but would not be testing any hypothesis : only observing patterns, or testing predictions. Maybe we should appreciate that better, and understand that &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; is not just using the scientific method : &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; is a also a big adventure of communication, funding, coordination, techniques and methods, relations, journals, and even policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s important to distinguish hypothesis from predictions; because it takes us away, as researchers, from the desire to fit the routine of &amp;ldquo;introduction, hypothesis, methods, results&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, and embrace the fact that &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt; is a more complex affair that require adaptability and innovation. But more simply, it&amp;rsquo;s important to come back to the roots of our profession, and take the time to understand the basic concepts that we might sometimes forget and brush away. If you took the time to read this article - and if I made a good job writing it -, then we&amp;rsquo;re hopefully already part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Veganism and climate change</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/veganism_and_climate_change/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/post/veganism_and_climate_change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So called &amp;ldquo;vegan&amp;rdquo; diets and lifestyle have been a subject of debate, controversy, but also interest those past few years. The number of people trying this lifestyle &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2020/oct/26/veganuary-movement-plant-based-food#:~:text=The%20UK%2Dbased%20campaign%2C%20which,2019%20and%20170%2C000%20in%202018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;have been soaring in the last decade&lt;/a&gt;; activists have been publishing more and more &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dominionmovement.com/watch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;well-known documentaries revealing the dark side of animal agriculture&lt;/a&gt;; and many scientific studies have been advocating for the potential benefits of the lifestyle for the environment and climate change, as echoed by a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/srccl/chapter/chapter-5/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;special report of the IPCC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, for many of us, veganism is a difficult and touchy subject. The whole concept can feel like an undeserved attack on traditions, jobs, or on other things that we hold dear. And yet, most of us agree with its ethical premises : we don&amp;rsquo;t like the idea of hurting or killing animals when it&amp;rsquo;s not needed for our survival, and especially not when it&amp;rsquo;s for pleasure, comfort or habits, and that&amp;rsquo;s just what veganism is. In fact, the original definition from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vegansociety.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Vegan Society&lt;/a&gt; (the oldest vegan organisation in the world which first coined the term) says :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veganism is a philosophy and way of living which seeks to exclude—as far as is possible and practicable—all forms of exploitation of, and cruelty to, animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is something that most of us would certainly find noble. But the resulting tension between following those principles - or being asked to - and trying to protect things we hold dear can lead to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20200203-the-hidden-biases-that-drive-anti-vegan-hatred&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;severe anti-vegan bias&lt;/a&gt; that can be quite hard to overcome. I know that it has been hard on me for quite some time, and that I&amp;rsquo;m not completely free of it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bias, associated with the incredible economic and ideological power of the animal agriculture industry, can make things hard to piece out when we look at the science behind vegan lifestyles. Some studies funded by the industry have been criticized by the scientific community; while the results of others have been exaggerated by activists to fit their narrative. &lt;a href=&#34;https://sydneyuniversitypress.com.au/products/128398&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Whole books are now dedicated to analyzing the process of deception&lt;/a&gt; steaming from there forces. Really, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big current talking point about veganism concerns its ability to help us reduce our impacts on the environment, and especially on climate change. If one should summarized why in two sentences, we could say that it&amp;rsquo;s all about &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecological_efficiency&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ecological efficiency&lt;/a&gt; : at each level of a food chain, a great amount of energy coming from the level before is lost. Therefore, eating animals or they secretions imply that a great deal of the energy given to them as food - plants - will not be transformed as food for humans, but lost for the metabolism of the animal that is fed from. Meanwhile, eating plants avoids this loss - doubly so because plants are &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autotroph&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;autotrophic beings&lt;/a&gt;. This is why, in a very paradoxical way, eating plants instead of animals means that we require much less plants to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I got interested in this subject, I came into the opportunity of updating an article concerning veganism on the famous website &lt;a href=&#34;https://skepticalscience.com/veganism.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Skeptical Science&lt;/a&gt;, made by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.climatechangecommunication.org/portfolio-view/john-cook/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;John Cook&lt;/a&gt; and his colleagues. While not perfect by any mean, I always admired the attempt at scientific rigor and communication that the site strives for. And so, after rounds of writing and peer-review, my version is now online. I think that it does a pretty great job at giving a broad picture of the topic, and its subtleties. The short answer is that yes, veganism can be a great way to reduce our impacts on the environment, with a pretty clear consensus emerging from recent studies and reports; but that it won&amp;rsquo;t save the world by itself, and that other behavioral changes (like not using a car or not taking the plane) have a bigger impact on our &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Climate_footprint&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;climate footprint&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&#34;cta-group&#34;&gt;
  
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://skepticalscience.com/veganism.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34; class=&#34;btn btn-primary px-3 py-3&#34;&gt;Wanna check out my article on Skeptical Science ? Click here !&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  
  
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is just touching the &amp;ldquo;environmental&amp;rdquo; argument for veganism, and not even touching the other environmental aspects (such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/environmental-impacts-of-food&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;land-use, freshwater use, eutrophication, and biodiversity&lt;/a&gt;). Whatever the truth of the matter, I believe that our ethics always go first; that&amp;rsquo;s why none of us would start eating dogs, even if it was clearly proven that this would help fight climate change. Because of this, I recommend taking a closer look at what it really is to kill an animal; to imagine what we would feel if we were the ones slicing their throat, and facing their terrified gaze, all in order to eat a steak whose taste will be forgotten in a matter of minutes. And that if it is something that we couldn&amp;rsquo;t do ourselves out of compassion, kindness and courage, maybe it is something that we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pay for either.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Veganism the best way to reduce carbon emissions?</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/publication/hardy-veganism-best-way-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/publication/hardy-veganism-best-way-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>L&#39;aménagement forestier inéquien : Solution ou mirage d&#39;une foresterie durable ?</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/publication/hardy-amenagement-forestier-inequien-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/publication/hardy-amenagement-forestier-inequien-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating forest roads is necessary to determine the impacts of forest management on habitat amount and fragmentation (QCBS)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-qcbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-qcbs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Poster_2021_Clement_Hardy.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is perceived as offering attractive trade-offs between wood production, and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties persist about its impacts, due to the distribution of harvesting areas and the construction of forest roads over larger areas than the most traditional even-aged development. We have been exploring these impacts on the composition and fragmentation of a landscape for more than a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this, we used the spatially explicit LANDIS-II simulation model and a new extension that simulates the evolution of the forest road network. We simulated 30 development scenarios in a landscape of the Mauricie region by varying the use of uneven-aged management methods and the aggregation of cuts. Our results show that, in comparison with even-aged management management, uneven-aged management increases the density and operational costs of the forest road network, the amount of forest with old tree cohorts, and the per se fragmentation of these forests. In addition, in the boreal forest to the north of the landscape, forest fires tended to fragment old forests despite forest management, reducing the differences between management strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged management must depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation related to natural disturbances, and the perceived effects of per se fragmentation in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of cuts can reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but is unlikely to fully compensate for them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 types of software you should start using for your research</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/post/3_softwares_to_use/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/post/3_softwares_to_use/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As human knowledge accumulates and our daily lives become ever more busy, it&amp;rsquo;s not wonder that we start feeling overwelmed as researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our human brain might be an amazing tool to discover and understand the world around us when compared to a cat&amp;rsquo;s or a dog&amp;rsquo;s equivalent, but it is still both biased and limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, there exist many different tools that can help us to compensate for these issues. And the wonderful news is that they are &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, that they do not contain advertising, and that they do not sell information about yourself or your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a list of 3 open-source software that changed my life as a PhD student and early researcher, by allowing me to &lt;strong&gt;organize my references, my notes and my files&lt;/strong&gt; like never before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;joplin&#34;&gt;Joplin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Joplin_logo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joplin is a note-taking application with many features.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an open-source and completely free software that allows you to create notes in the &amp;ldquo;Markdown&amp;rdquo; writing language, and to organize them in &amp;ldquo;notebooks&amp;rdquo;, and associate them with tags. &lt;strong&gt;It is an excellent alternative to software such as Evernote or Microsoft One Note&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, Joplin allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather all your written or graphic information in one place&lt;/strong&gt;: your class notes, your thoughts, your projects, your recipes, your shopping lists, your to-do lists, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find all this information very quickly&lt;/strong&gt; (in a few seconds) thanks to the search tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use it on any computer&lt;/strong&gt; (Windows, Mac, Linux) and &lt;strong&gt;on any phone&lt;/strong&gt; (android, IOs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Synchronize your data on the cloud you choose&lt;/strong&gt; : Nextcloud (see below), Google Drive, One Drive, etc. So you can have all your data written everywhere, all the time, on any media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a fully customizable interface&lt;/strong&gt; that allows you to focus totally on what you are writing, so that you don&amp;rsquo;t waste time and attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export your notes in many ways&lt;/strong&gt;, with a format (markdown) that can be read anywhere and at any time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically manage the images and files you insert in your notes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically edit your notes&lt;/strong&gt; (so you can go back at any time if you made a mistake).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And much more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joplin is an amazing software to try your hand at note-taking tools, and maybe even at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; method !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other wondful alternatives include &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zettlr.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zettlr&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://obsidian.md/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt;. However, I think that Joplin is the best place to start if you&amp;rsquo;re not used to such apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download Joplin, take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://joplinapp.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;zotero&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./zotero_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zotero is a bibliography management software.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having complete and rigorous bibliography information is necessary in academic documents (thesis, dissertation, article). It can also be very important for blog or website posts, videos, scripts, and many others. It can additionally be very useful for managing personal resources. The bibliography information of a document is called &amp;lsquo;meta-data&amp;rsquo;, i.e. data &lt;em&gt;about the document&lt;/em&gt;, but &lt;em&gt;outside the document&lt;/em&gt; (its title, its publication date, its author(s), etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zotero allows you to :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easily save all the metadata associated with a document&lt;/strong&gt; (title, authors, place of publication, date, URL, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Associate notes or tags&lt;/strong&gt; to each reference or document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sort these references by category&lt;/strong&gt;s, or by their characteristics to find them easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download associated PDF files&lt;/strong&gt; when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export bibliography files&lt;/strong&gt; that contain all the details of the references, so that they can be inserted into a document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insert and manage the bibliography of a document&lt;/strong&gt; in Microsoft Word, Libreoffice or Google Doc using its plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zotero have a wonderful community that devellops incredible plugins such as Better BibTex, Zotfile or MDnotes. All of these will allow you to connect your Zotero database to other software such as Joplin, Zettlr and Obsidian, or to export the annotations that you make in your &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download Zotero, you can go on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;its website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;nextcloud&#34;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Nextcloud_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nextcloud is a cloud software like Google Drive, allowing to host files, but also containing multiple very useful applications. However, unlike Google Drive, it is open-source and free&lt;/strong&gt;. You only need to host it on a server yourself, or choose an host (free, or subscription-based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud allows you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have an online file storage space that is totally yours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have access to lots of different applications all open-source&lt;/strong&gt; that allow you to manage to-do lists, &lt;em&gt;kanban boards&lt;/em&gt;, calendars, contacts, notes, recipes, maps, track your phone&amp;rsquo;s location, collaborate on documents, and much more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nextcloud is an incredible way to boost your productivity by organizing simply across devices, and I cannot recommand it enough. It is also perfect to host your Joplin notes in the cloud, or your Zettlr or Obsidian files. You can even save the &lt;code&gt;.pdf&lt;/code&gt; files of your zotero database with it ! Best of all, most of Nextcloud&amp;rsquo;s apps can synchronize very easily with your phone. Tasks on your phone ? Check. Calendar ? Check. Kanban boards ? Check. Recipes ? Check. The list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find an host or download nextcloud and host it yourself, you should look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextcloud.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the project&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;remember-to-contribute-&#34;&gt;Remember to contribute !&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these incredible programs are free, but they all represent hours and hours of hard work, along with the work of creating documentation, beautiful websites, and easy-to-use installer for people like you or me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using open-source software can be describe as a particular way of life, as these are often much more respectful of your privacy than software made by companies such as Microsoft, Google, Facebook, or even Macintosh. But the price to pay is often on the shoulder of the devellopers : they are the ones investing the work needed, and will often have nothing for themselves if the venture fails, with no add revenues or revenues from selling your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, &lt;strong&gt;if you start using one of these programs, remember to take the time to make a donation or a contribution to the project that they represent&lt;/strong&gt;. If the software pleases you, the team behind it have certainly earned it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;want-to-know-more-&#34;&gt;Want to know more ?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Logo_atelier_organisation_EN.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about these software, how to use them and their functionalities, you should take a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;free online workshop&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve created to help you discover them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just an afternoon before you, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn the most important thing about them; but you&amp;rsquo;ll also learn some great methods to use them properly, and even in tandem together !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (University of Alaska Fairbank)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-university-of-alaska-fairbank/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-university-of-alaska-fairbank/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction extend over larger areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management on the composition and fragmentation of a 800 000ha landscape over a 150 years-planning horizon. To that end, we used the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension that simulates the expansion of the forest road network. We compared 30 different management scenarios that varied the proportion of even- and uneven-aged management, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads on a forested landscape of Mauricie (Québec, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences in landscape fragmentation between even-aged and uneven-aged management were reduced in the northern region of the landscape, in the boreal forest, where forest fires tended to fragment old forests irrespectively of the type of management approach employed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged over even-aged management should depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation resulting from natural disturbances, and on the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to compensate them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Open-source and Organisation workshop</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/project/open_source_org_workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/project/open_source_org_workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-description&#34;&gt;📑 Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A free workshop to help people discover open-source software, in order to better organize themselves and the information they come in contact with on a daily basis. You can do it by yourself in an afternoon&amp;rsquo;s time by doing the guided exercises and documentation at &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (IBFRA)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-ibfra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-ibfra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🏆 This presentation won the &amp;ldquo;Best presentation&amp;rdquo; award for this annual conference of the IBFRA&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction can impact the composition and fragmentation of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management at the landscape scale and on a planning horizon of 150 years by using the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension allowing for the dynamic simulation of the forest road network. We simulated a landscape containing boreal forest in the Mauricie Region of Québec with 30 different management scenarios where we varied the use of uneven-aged management methods, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that when compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests of the landscape, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences of fragmentation of the landscape between even-aged and uneven-aged management were lower in the northern region containing more boreal forest, as forest fires tended to fragment the old forests of the landscape in spite of any forest management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that selecting uneven-aged over even-aged management should be closely linked to how fragmentation and habitat are defined, to the patterns of fragmentation as a result of natural disturbances, and to the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help to reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to entirely compensate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating forest roads is necessary to determine the impacts of forest management on habitat amount and fragmentation (ESA)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-esa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/simulating-forest-roads-is-necessary-to-determine-the-impacts-of-forest-management-on-habitat-amount-and-fragmentation-esa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Poster_ESA_V4.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services related to biodiversity conservation, carbon storage, and social acceptability. While benefits of uneven-aged management have been reported at the stand-scale and for short time periods, uncertainties remain concerning its impacts for longer time periods and broader spatial scales. Of concern is the impact of forest roads. Indeed, uneven-aged forestry requires that silvicultural operations extend over larger forest areas than even-aged forestry in order to harvest the same volume of wood. Consequently, uneven-aged forestry may require a larger and more permanent forest road network to reach distant stands over shorter rotation periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management on the composition and fragmentation of a 800 000 ha landscape over a 150 years-planning horizon. We used the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension that simulates the expansion of the forest road network. We compared 30 different management scenarios that varied the proportion of even- and uneven-aged management, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads on a forested landscape of Mauricie (Québec, Canada).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests, but also the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences in landscape fragmentation between even-aged and uneven-aged management were reduced in the northern region of the landscape, in the boreal forest, where forest fires tended to fragment old forests irrespectively of the type of management approach employed. We conclude that the choice of uneven-aged over even-aged management should depend on the type of fragmentation and habitat considered, the patterns of fragmentation resulting from natural disturbances, and on the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to compensate them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organization and open-source workshop</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/organization-and-open-source-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/organization-and-open-source-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our modern lives put us in constant contact with information. So much information that it can be very difficult to structure it, but also to find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different softwares exist today to lighten the work that we ask our brains to manage this information. However, these programs are often owned by large corporations that are unclear about whether they have access to the stored data, and whether they share it with other companies or intelligence agencies. They also have methods or workings that are sometimes very rigid, and that may not be suitable for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To leanr more, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://klemet.github.io/Workshop-Organization-EN/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Workshop to learn to use the FRS module for LANDIS-II</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/workshop-to-learn-to-use-the-frs-module-for-landis-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/workshop-to-learn-to-use-the-frs-module-for-landis-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Forest Roads Simulation (FRS) module is an extension of the LANDIS-II Forest Landscape Model (FLM). It was created so as to help researchers in ecology to take into account the constructions of forest roads when studying the impacts of forest management on forest landscapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To learn more, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://klemet.github.io/frs-module-workshop/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://klemet.github.io/frs-module-workshop/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🏆 Long-term impacts of uneven-aged development on the quantity and fragmentation of old-growth forest in a landscape (CEF)</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-cef/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-development-on-the-quantity-and-fragmentation-of-old-growth-forest-in-a-landscape-cef/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;🏆 This presentation won the &amp;ldquo;Best presentation&amp;rdquo; award for this annual symposium of the CEF&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach when compared to more traditional even-aged methods, offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services. But uncertainties remain concerning its impacts on longer time periods and broader spatial scales, where harvesting activities and forest roads construction can impact the composition and fragmentation of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, we explored the impacts of uneven-aged management at the landscape scale and on a planning horizon of 150 years by using the forest landscape model LANDIS-II, along with an extension allowing for the dynamic simulation of the forest road network. We simulated a landscape containing boreal forest in the Mauricie Region of Québec with 30 different management scenarios where we varied the use of uneven-aged management methods, the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and the presence of pre-existing forest roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results show that when compared with even-aged management, uneven-aged management increased both the quantity of forest roads and their operational costs, the fragmentation per se of the older forests of the landscape, and the quantity of forest with older tree cohorts. In addition, differences of fragmentation of the landscape between even-aged and uneven-aged management were lower in the northern region containing more boreal forest, as forest fires tended to fragment the old forests of the landscape in spite of any forest management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conclude that selecting uneven-aged over even-aged management should be closely linked to how fragmentation and habitat are defined, to the patterns of fragmentation as a result of natural disturbances, and to the perceived effects of fragmentation per se in the landscape. We also conclude that aggregation of the harvested areas could help to reduce the negative impacts of uneven-aged management, but that they are unlikely to entirely compensate them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long term impacts of uneven-aged management</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily Activity Patterns and Co-Occurrence of Duikers Revealed by an Intensive Camera Trap Survey across Central African Rainforests</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/publication/houngbegnon-daily-activity-patterns-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/publication/houngbegnon-daily-activity-patterns-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Forest Roads Simulation module for LANDIS-II</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/project/frs_module_landis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/project/frs_module_landis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-description&#34;&gt;📑 Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FRS (Forest Roads Simulation) module is an extension for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.landis-ii.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LANDIS-II&lt;/a&gt; model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It allows any user to dynamically simulate the evolution of the forest road network in the simulated landscape of LANDIS-II. It does so by creating roads to cells that are harvested by a harvest module (such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.landis-ii.org/extensions/base-harvest&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Base Harvest&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.landis-ii.org/extensions/biomass-harvest&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Biomass Harvest&lt;/a&gt;), while reducing the costs of construction of roads as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Klemet/LANDIS-II-Forest-Roads-Simulation-module&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Learn more on the GitHub page of the project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The influence of forest road networks on the long term impacts of uneven-aged management</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/the-influence-of-forest-road-networks-on-the-long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/the-influence-of-forest-road-networks-on-the-long-term-impacts-of-uneven-aged-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Uneven-aged forest management is currently seen by many forest ecologists as an extensive management approach offering interesting compromises between timber production and other important ecosystem services such as biodiversity conservation, carbon storage, and social acceptability. While the benefits of uneven-aged management have been reported at the stand-scale and on short time periods, uncertainties remain concerning the impacts of uneven-aged management on longer time and wider spatial scales. Of concern are the impact of forest roads, as uneven-aged management necessitate more permanent roads and an increased road usage in order to accommodate shorter harvest rotations. These could in turn increase permanent forest lost, fauna road mortality, carbon emissions and operational costs for the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore this question, we compared the impact of uneven-aged management with that of even-aged management at large time and spatial scales. We created a road extension for the LANDIS-II landscape simulation model, whose goal is to simulate the construction of forest roads to reach harvesting areas in a dynamic and spatially explicit way. Road trajectories are computed by minimizing construction costs according to existing roads, elevation, topography, water bodies, and soil types. We developed 20 scenarios with different proportions of harvested areas managed with uneven-aged or even aged management methods, for a given harvest wood volume. The scenarios also differed in the level of aggregation of the harvested areas, and in the presence of a pre-existing forest roads. We tested these scenarios over a planning horizon of 300 years on a landscape of 5 million hectares in Mauricie, Canada, and measured several characteristics of the road network for each scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results will further our understanding of the long-term impacts of management strategies in forested landscapes, and will also open new opportunities to explore the impact of forest roads around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roads to conservation</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/roads-to-conservation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/roads-to-conservation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The caribou (Rangifer tarandus) faces many different pressures throughout Québec, making it a vulnerable species. In particular, forest roads, numerous throughout the province, increase caribou mortality. Indeed, forest roads increase predation by the grey wolf (Canis lupus) that uses them to move quickly through the landscape to track its prey. Moreover, forest roads also increase habitat fragmentation; which in turn generates stress, habitat avoidance, and ultimately affect feeding patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ministère des Forêts, de la Faune et des Parcs du Québec (MFFP), in charge of forest management and fauna protection, is faced with the difficult task of designing forest roads necessary to maintain the viability of the forest industry while reducing their negative impact on the caribou. As part of an internship at the MFFP, I have developed an open-source GIS-based tool capable of exploring different strategies for building forest road networks. The goal of this tool is to prevent the disturbance of areas important to the caribou populations, and to detect existing roads that could be removed in order to improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool had to respect many criteria: it had to be quick and easy to use, while being flexible enough to explore different user-defined scenarios. Each scenario generates a forest road network that expands across the forest areas to be harvested. In this presentation, I will briefly describe the difficulties faced to solve the very complex problem of optimizing a road network. I will also explain how I simulated the wood flux through the network in order to determine its most important roads.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Forest Road Network Plugin for QGIS</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/project/forest_roads_plugin_qgis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/project/forest_roads_plugin_qgis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;-description&#34;&gt;📑 Description&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This plugin contains several algorithms destined to help the user create an optimized forest road network, based on the topography of the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user must first create or input a &amp;ldquo;cost map&amp;rdquo;, which describes the cost of construction of a road on a pixel. Then, different algorithms allows the user to create the road network, then simulate the fluxes of wood going through it (transport via timber trucks), then decide the width and type of each road segment according to this flux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Klemet/ForestRoadNetworkPluginForQGIS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Learn more on the GitHub page of the project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new LANDIS-II module to study the effects of roads on forest landscapes</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/a-new-landis-ii-module-to-study-the-effects-of-roads-on-forest-landscapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/a-new-landis-ii-module-to-study-the-effects-of-roads-on-forest-landscapes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./poster_final_colloque_cef_2019.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LANDIS-II is a spatially explicit model to simulate the evolution of a forest landscape represented by a raster. Each cell in it represents a piece of the surface of it, and the LANDIS-II user can choose from different extensions in order to represent processes that impact the plant succession of the landscape forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the existing extensions make it possible to model forest fires, biological epidemics, chablis, and the effect of logging on wood harvesting. However, the goal of the LANDIS-II Foundation, which is responsible for the development of the model, is more ambitious: interested researchers are explicitly invited to develop new extensions thanks to a structure that allows extensions to be easily grafted onto the &amp;ldquo;heart&amp;rdquo; of the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in this context that our research project fits in, which aims to explore the effects of equitable and inequal forest management methods on large spatial and temporal scales. The more extensive uneven-aged forest management methods are currently presented by many researchers as an important alternative to the even-aged methods, but the impacts of their use have not yet been considered on a large scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To distinguish the effects of these methods at the landscape scale, however, we must take into account a process that has, to our knowledge, never been modeled in such a context: the construction of forest paths necessary for access to stands. To this end, we have started the development of a new extension for LANDIS-II. This extension will simulate the development and maintenance of a network of forest paths in a landscaped landscape, and the costs and effects associated with these paths. We will combine the use of this module with different forest management scenarios, in order to observe how the use of the Equian and Inequian methods influence the quantity and structure of paths in the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do I cut this forest landscape for you? - Influence of space tessellation methods on modeling in forest ecology</title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/talk/how-do-i-cut-this-forest-landscape-for-you-influence-of-space-tessellation-methods-on-modeling-in-forest-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/talk/how-do-i-cut-this-forest-landscape-for-you-influence-of-space-tessellation-methods-on-modeling-in-forest-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, thanks to the increase in the computational capabilities of our computers, the fields of ecology and forestry have seen the appearance of new tools within them. Among these are spatially explicit models, in which processes and represented entities are placed in space. These models, now widely used and developed in number, then make it possible to simulate different scenarios to better understand or better predict the evolution of a studied system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to simplify the use of these models and the calculations they generate, the spatial dimension of the model is generally &amp;ldquo;discretized&amp;rdquo;. By this act, the space is then divided into more or less small cells depending on the resolution used. The geometric shape most used by modelers to cut out space is that of the square, which makes it possible to create regular grids, in addition to other advantages. This choice of geometry to discretize space can however be questioned, while it has been shown that it could have strong impacts on the results of a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then decided to focus on the impact of this choice on the functioning of spatially explicit models in forest ecology. For this, we will reproduce the operation of several existing models well known in the field, and which represent an important process for forest ecosystems (e.g. natural disturbances). We will then run these models on different grids (e.g. square, hexagonal, irregular, etc.) to observe the effects of these on the results obtained. Results obtained from preliminary work suggest that such effects may indeed be important, but not for all types of processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://klemet.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://klemet.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
